Guide to the Breakbeat Lenny Archive, 1980-2004.
Breakbeat Lenny Archive
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Breakbeat Lenny Archive, 1980-2004.
8052
Roberts
2 linear feet.
Sound recordings, printed material
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
The core of the collection is a series of rare soundboard recordings of live performances taken directly from the soundboard, also party flyers.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
The collection was assembled by Lenny Roberts, better known as Breakbeat Lenny, a DJ who assembled the seminal compilation series “Ultimate Breaks and Beats” throughout the 1980s.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
The core of the collection is a series of rare soundboard recordings of live performances taken directly from the soundboard, with clear labels indicating dates, venues, and performers. It is likely that these were the master tapes from which "battle tapes" of live performances were made and distributed in the South Bronx. Also includes are Lenny's personal copies of 13 of the original 25 Ultimate Breaks and Beats compilation LPs; 127 hip hop party fliers, and a selection of publications relating to record collecting and DJing.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Roberts, Lenny.
Subjects:
Hip-hop.; Rap (Music); Hip-hop -- New York (N.Y.); Street art.; Disk jockeys.
Places:
Bronx (New York, N.Y.)
INFORMATION FOR USERS
SERIES LIST
Series I. Sound Recordings
Boxes 1-3
Series II. Flyers
Box 4
Series III. Publications
Boxes 5-6
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I. Sound Recordings
  - T-Connection, October 10, 1980; TR-9046 (Box 1)
    Performers: DJ Afrika Bambaataa, DJ Jazzy Jay
  - Hunts Point Palace, June 6, 1981; TR-9047 (Box 1)
    Performers: Charlie Chase, Mean Gene & Co., Grandwizzard Theodore & Grandmaster Caz
  - Hunts Point Palace, June 6, 1981; TR-9048 (Box 1)
    Performers: DJ Jazzy Jay, DJ Breakout, Funky 4 + 1, DJ Afrika Bambaataa, Mean Gene & Co.
  - Savoy Manor, July 17, 1981; TR-9049 (Box 1)
    Performers: Kenny Ken, Charlie Chase
  - 100 Park, August 6, 1981; TR-9050 (Box 1)
    Performers: Unknown
  - Castle Hill Park, August 22, 1981; TR-9051 (Box 1)
  - Bronx River, August 29, 1981; TR-9052 (Box 1)
  - T-Connection, October 11, 1981; TR-9053 (Box 1)
    Performers: Charlie Chase, Cold Crush Brothers
  - T-Connection, November 12, 1981; TR-9054 (Box 1)
  - T-Connection, November 13, 1981; TR-9055 (Box 1)
  - Bronx River, November 14, 1981; TR-9056 (Box 1)
  - Stardust Ballroom, February 20, 1982; TR-9057 (Box 1)
    Performers: Cold Crush Brothers, Touch of Class
  - Stardust Ballroom, February 20, 1982; TR-9058 (Box 1)
    Performers: Cold Crush Brothers, Jazzy 5 MC's
  - T-Connection, October 10, 1980; 1428 (Box 2)
  - T-Connection, October 10, 1980; 1429 (Box 2)
  - 100 Park, August 6, 1981; 1430 (Box 2)
  - 100 Park, August 6, 1981; 1431 (Box 2)
  - Castle Hill Park, August 22, 1981; 1432 (Box 2)
  - Bronx River, August 29, 1981; 1433 (Box 2)
  - Bronx River, August 29, 1981; 1434 (Box 2)
  - T-Connection, October 11, 1981; 1435 (Box 2)
  - T-Connection, October 11, 1981; 1436 (Box 2)
  - Bronx River, November 14, 1981; 1437 (Box 2)
  - Bronx River, November 14, 1981; 1438 (Box 2)
  - Hunts Point Palace, June 6, 1981; 1439 (Box 2)
  - Hunts Point Palace, June 6, 1981; 1440 (Box 2)
  - Hunts Point Palace, June 6, 1981; 1441 (Box 2)
  - Hunts Point Palace, June 6, 1981; 1442 (Box 2)
  - Savoy Manor, July 17, 1981; 1443 (Box 2)
  - Savoy Manor, July 17, 1981; 1444 (Box 2)
  - T-Connection, November 12, 1981; 1445 (Box 2)
  - T-Connection, November 12, 1981; 1446 (Box 2)
  - T-Connection, November 13, 1981; 1447 (Box 2)
  - T-Connection, November 13, 1981; 1448 (Box 2)
  - Stardust Ballroom, February 20, 1982; 1449 (Box 2)
    (CD is mislabeled: says 2/2/82)
  - Stardust Ballroom, February 20, 1982; 1450 (Box 2)
  - Stardust Ballroom, February 20, 1982; 1451 (Box 2)
  - Stardust Ballroom, February 20, 1982; 1452 (Box 2)
  - Harlem World, 1981; 1453 (Box 2)
    Performers: Cold Crush Brothers, Fantastic 5 MC's
  - Rock and Roll Hall of Fame and Museum, 1999; 1454 (Box 2)
    Performers: MARE 139 RTW XL-Mixmaster
  - Hip Hop Labels, 1455 (Box 2)
    handwritten note: "mega tons of early rap labels scanned"
  - Hip Hop MP3's, 1456 (Box 2)
  - Hip Hop MP3's, 1457 (Box 2)
  - Hip Hop MP3's, 1458 (Box 2)
  - Hip Hop MP3's, 1459 (Box 2)
  - Hip Hop MP3's, 1460 (Box 2)
  - Hip Hop MP3's, 1461 (Box 2)
  - Street Beat Records, 1987; SR-1185 (Box 3)
    Album: Ultimate Breaks & Beats - SBR 513
    Performers: various artists
  - Street Beat Records, 1988; SR-1186 (Box 3)
    Album: Ultimate Breaks & Beats - SBR 518
    2 copies
  - Street Beat Records, 1986; SR-1187 (Box 3)
    Ultimate Breaks & Beats - SBR 501 Album:
  - Street Beat Records, 1986; SR-1188 (Box 3)
    Ultimate Breaks & Beats - SBR 502 Album:
  - Street Beat Records, 1986; SR-1189 (Box 3)
    Album: Ultimate Breaks & Beats - SBR 503
  - Street Beat Records, 1986; SR-1190 (Box 3)
    Album: Ultimate Breaks & Beats - SBR 507
  - Street Beat Records, [1986?]; SR-1191 (Box 3)
    Album: Ultimate Breaks & Beats - SBR 509
    Unopened
  - Street Beat Records, 1986; SR-1192 (Box 3)
    Album: Ultimate Breaks & Beats - SBR 510
  - Street Beat Records, 1988; SR-1193 (Box 3)
    Album: Ultimate Breaks & Beats - SBR 519
  - Street Beat Records, 1988; SR-1194 (Box 3)
    Album: Ultimate Breaks & Beats - SBR 520
  - Street Beat Records, 1989; SR-1195 (Box 3)
    Album: Ultimate Breaks & Beats - SBR 521
  - Street Beat Records, 1989; SR-1196 (Box 3)
    Album: Ultimate Breaks & Beats - SBR 522
  - Street Beat Records, 1990; SR-1197 (Box 3)
    Album: Ultimate Breaks & Beats - SBR 524
  - Unknown, SR-1198 (Box 3)
    Album: Octopus Breaks Vol 4
    2 copies with obscured labels, in pink jackets
- Series II. Flyers
  - 3rd Ave. Ballroom, February 16, 1979; A 1 (Box 4)
    Flier designer: Buddy Esquire
  - Ecstasy Garage Disco, June 20, 1980; A 2 (Box 4)
  - Ecstasy Garage Disco, June 21, 1980; A 3 (Box 4)
  - Ecstasy Garage Disco, November 14, 1980; A 4 (Box 4)
  - Remington Boys Club, December 12, 1980; A 5 (Box 4)
  - Ecstasy Garage Disco, February 12, 1981; A 6 (Box 4)
  - I.S. 167, March 7, 1981; A 7 (Box 4)
    I.S. means "intermediate school"
  - T-Connection, April 4, 1981; A 8 (Box 4)
  - Ecstasy Garage Disco, April 4, 1981; A 9 (Box 4)
  - T-Connection, April 10, 1981; A 10 (Box 4)
  - Ecstasy Garage Disco, April 24, 25 1981; A 11 (Box 4)
  - T-Connection, May 29, 1981; A 12 (Box 4)
  - Morris H.S., June 12, 1981; A 13 (Box 4)
  - T-Connection, November 20, 21 1981; A 14 (Box 4)
  - Taft H.S. & Lafayette Houses, January 8, 9 1982; A 15 (Box 4)
  - Kips Bay Boys Club, February 13, 1982; A 16 & 17 (Box 4)
  - Stardust Ballroom, February 20, 1982; A 18 (Box 4)
  - James Monroe H.S., April 11, 1980; A 19 (Box 4)
    Flier designer: Eddie Ed
  - T-Connection, August 15,16 1980; A 20 (Box 4)
  - T-Connection, September 12, 1980; A 21 (Box 4)
  - Ecstasy Garage Disco, October 3, 1980; A 22 (Box 4)
  - T-Connection, October 11, 1980; A 23 (Box 4)
  - Audubon Ballroom, October 24, 1980; A 24 (Box 4)
  - Ecstasy Garage Disco, November 1, 1980; A 25 (Box 4)
  - T-Connection, November 2, 1980; A 26 (Box 4)
  - Bronx River Center & T-Connection, November 7, 8 1980; A 27 (Box 4)
  - T-Connection, November 21, 1980; A 28 (Box 4)
  - T-Connection, December 19, 1980; A 29 (Box 4)
  - T-Connection, February 20, 1981; A 30 (Box 4)
  - T-Connection, February 27, 1981; A 31 (Box 4)
  - Roller World Skating Rink, March 12, 1981; A 32 (Box 4)
  - T-Connection, October 11, 1981; A 33 (Box 4)
  - Bronx River Center & T-Connection, November 13, 14 1981; A 34 & 35 (Box 4)
    2 different flyers for the same 2 parties
  - P.A.L. Webster Ave., November 28, 1981; A 36 (Box 4)
    P.A.L. = police athletic league
  - T-Connection, December 11, 1981; A 37 (Box 4)
  - Harlem World, December 18, 1981; A 38 (Box 4)
  - T-Connection, December 19, 1981; A 39 (Box 4)
  - Bronx River Center Annex, December 31, 1981; A 40 (Box 4)
  - Kips Bay Boys Club, January 9, 1982; A 41 (Box 4)
  - Kips Bay Boys Club, January 30, 1982; A 42 (Box 4)
  - Ecstasy Garage Disco, November 27, 1980; B 1 (Box 4)
    Flier designer: Phase 2
  - Printing H.S., December 6, 1980; B 2 (Box 4)
  - Ecstasy Garage Disco, December 12, 1980; B 3 (Box 4)
  - T-Connection, February 21, 1981; B 4 (Box 4)
  - Audubon Ballroom, February 27, 1981; B 5 (Box 4)
  - Stevenson H.S., March 20, 1981; B 6 (Box 4)
  - Harlem World, May 24, 1981; B 7 (Box 4)
  - Hunts Point Palace, June 6, 1981; B 8 (Box 4)
  - Your Spot, July 10, 1981; B 9 (Box 4)
  - Harlem World, August 28, 1981; B 10 (Box 4)
  - Kips Bay Boys Club, September 25, 1981; B 11 (Box 4)
  - P.A.L. Webster Ave., December 26, 1981; B 12 (Box 4)
  - Negril, January 21, 1982; B 13 (Box 4)
    "Negrill" is spelled with 2 L's
  - Negril, March 11, 1982; B 14 (Box 4)
  - The Roxy, October 1, 1982; B 15 (Box 4)
  - Columbus Boys Club, May 9, 1980; B 16 (Box 4)
    Flier designer: Anthony Riley
  - Chez Amor, May 10, 1980; B 17 (Box 4)
  - Ecstasy Garage Disco, February 13, 1981; B 18 (Box 4)
  - Ecstasy Garage Disco, February 14, 1981; B 19 (Box 4)
  - Ecstasy Garage Disco, February 21, 1981; B 20 (Box 4)
  - Bronx River Center & Broadway International, November 12, 13 1982; B 21 (Box 4)
    Flier designer: Asam
  - Harlem World, May 28, 29 1983; B 22 (Box 4)
    Flier designer: Charly Rock
  - Harlem World, May 20, 21, 22, 29 1982; B 23 (Box 4)
    Flier designer: Danny Owite
  - T-Connection, November 27, 1980; B 24 (Box 4)
    Flier designer: Danny Tonge
  - Edenwald Center, October 30, 1981; B 25 (Box 4)
  - 1005 Lambert Center, November 20, 1982; B 26 (Box 4)
    Flier designer: Kool G
    This is out of alphabetical order because the designer was originally thought to be "Dr. Rock"
  - Edenwald Center, December 30, 1981; B 27 (Box 4)
    Flier designer: DJ Freeze
  - The Roxy, September 24, 1982; B 28 (Box 4)
    Flier designer: Futura
    Phase 2 helped design this
  - 35 Jackson Street Center, Yonkers, NY, December 20, 1980; B 29 (Box 4)
    Flier designer: Gill Rock
  - The Roxy, October 29, 1982; B 30 (Box 4)
    Flier designer: Justin X
  - Hoe Ave Boys Club, February 26, 1982; B 31 (Box 4)
    Flier designer: Kool Lance
  - Wheels Roller Rink, April 14, 1982; B 32 (Box 4)
  - 35 Jackson Street Center, Yonkers, NY, December 13, 1980; B 33 (Box 4)
    Flier designer: Master Kid
  - Bronx River Center & T-Connection, November 7, 8 1980; B 34 (Box 4)
    Flier designer: Poo 2
  - J.H.S. 131, October 24, 1981; B 35 (Box 4)
  - First City, May 6, 1983; B 36 (Box 4)
    Flier designer: Salsa Kenny
  - The Venue, London, January 19 - February 1979; B 37 (Box 4)
    Flier designer: Unknown
    January 19, 20, 21, 22, 25, 26, 27,31, February 1, 3, 4, 5, 17 1979
  - T-Connection, October 4, 1980; B 38 (Box 4)
  - T-Connection, October 12, 1980; B 39 (Box 4)
  - P.A.L. 123rd St., November 1, 1980; B 40 (Box 4)
  - T-Connection, November 22, 1980; B 41 (Box 4)
  - T-Connection, November 28, 1980; B 42 (Box 4)
  - Ecstasy Garage Disco, December 6, 1980; B 43 (Box 4)
  - 2045 Story Ave. - Boulevard Tower II, December 13, 1980; B 44 (Box 4)
  - T-Connection, December 20, 1980; B 45 (Box 4)
  - T-Connection, December 30, 1980; B 46 (Box 4)
  - T-Connection, March 13, 1981; B 47 (Box 4)
  - T-Connection, April 17, 1981; B 48 (Box 4)
    Flier designer: Sisco Kid
  - Mitchell Center, April 18, 1981; C 1 (Box 4)
  - T-Connection, May 1, 1981; C 2 (Box 4)
  - T-Connection, May 2, 1981; C 3 (Box 4)
  - T-Connection, May 8, 1981; C 4 (Box 4)
  - T-Connection, May 8, 1981; C 5 (Box 4)
  - 369th Regiment Armory, May 9, 1981; C 6 (Box 4)
  - Roller World Skating Rink, July 3, 1981; C 7 (Box 4)
  - Savoy Manor, July 17, 1981; C 8 (Box 4)
  - Mosque Roller Rink (Bridgport, Conn.), August 8, 1981; C 9 (Box 4)
  - Harlem World, October 2, 1981; C 10 (Box 4)
  - T-Connection, October 31, 1981; C 11 (Box 4)
  - T-Connection, November 25, 26 1981; C 12 (Box 4)
  - Wheels Roller Rink, December 28, 1981; C 13 (Box 4)
  - T-Connection, January 14, 1982; C 14 (Box 4)
  - B&B Disco, January 16, 1982; C 15 (Box 4)
  - Jacob Riis Center, January 22, 1982; C 16 (Box 4)
  - Bronx Skating Rink, February 27, 1982; C 17 (Box 4)
  - Harlem World, March 6, 1982; C 18 (Box 4)
  - Printing H.S. Gym, March 13, 1982; C 19 (Box 4)
  - Harlem World, April 9, 10 1982; C 20 (Box 4)
  - The Roxy, November 26, 1982; C 21 (Box 4)
  - The Roxy, December 3, 1982; C 22 (Box 4)
    possible designer: Futura
  - Reggae Lounge, December 9, 1982; C 23 (Box 4)
  - Negril, December 23, 1982; C 24 & 25 (Box 4)
    2 versions with slightly different design elements
  - The Roxy, December 24, 1982; C 26 (Box 4)
    possible designer: Justin X
  - Leland Houses, December 24, 1982; C 27 (Box 4)
  - Negril, February 28, 1983; C 28 (Box 4)
  - Leland Houses, March 19, 1983; C 29 (Box 4)
  - Underground, March 22, 1983; C 30 (Box 4)
  - The Roxy, June 18, 1983; C 31 & 32 (Box 4)
    2 copies; possible designer: Futura
  - "opposite 353 E. Houston Street (3 blocks east of 1st ave.)", August 27, 1983; C 33 (Box 4)
    possible venue name: Earth's Edge; possible designer: Phase 2
  - Savoy Manor, November 11, 1983; C 34 (Box 4)
  - Clarmont Gym, January 30, 1988; C 35 (Box 4)
    possible designer: A Magical #1
  - WHBI - 105.9 FM (DJ Nap radio show, weds 4am-5am), Unknown; C 36 (Box 4)
- Series III. Publications
  - Top R&B Singles 1942-1988, 1988 (Box n/a)
    Monograph by Joel Whitburn
    Book has a handwritten note inside the front cover
  - Yesterday's Memories, 1975 (Box 6)
    Volume #: 1 Issue #: 3
    The Hollywood Flames on cover
  - Yesterday's Memories, 1975 (Box 6)
    Volume #: 1 Issue #: 4
    "Special Baltimore/D.C. Issue" on cover
  - record eXchanger, 1972 (Box 6)
    Volume #: 2 Issue #: 6 (consecutive issue 11)
    The Penguins on cover
  - record eXchanger, 1972 (Box 6)
    Volume #: 3 Issue #: 1 (consecutive issue 12)
    The Four Buddies on cover
  - record eXchanger, 1973 (Box 6)
    Volume #: 3 Issue #: 3 (consecutive issue 14)
    Little Anthony & The Imperials on cover
  - record eXchanger, 1973 (Box 6)
    Volume #: 3 Issue #: 5 (consecutive issue 16)
    The Solitaires on cover
  - record eXchanger, 1974 (Box 6)
    Volume #: 4 Issue #: 1 (consecutive issue 17)
    Sam Cooke on cover
  - record eXchanger, 1975 (Box 6)
    Volume #: 4 Issue #: 3 (consecutive issue 19)
    Savannah Churchill on cover
  - record eXchanger, 1976 (Box 6)
    Volume #: 4 Issue #: 6 (consecutive issue 22)
    The Dells on cover
  - Bim Bam Boom, December - January 1972 (Box 6)
    The Five Satins on cover
  - Bim Bam Boom, February - March 1972 (Box 6)
    The Flamingos on cover
  - Bim Bam Boom, April - May 1972 (Box 6)
    Volume #: 1 Issue #: 5
    The Cadillacs on cover
  - Bim Bam Boom, July 1972 (Box 6)
    Volume #: 1 Issue #: 6
    The Platters on cover
  - Bim Bam Boom, September 1972 (Box 6)
    Volume #: 1 Issue #: 7
  - Bim Bam Boom, December 1972 (Box 6)
    Volume #: 1 Issue #: 8
  - Bim Bam Boom, 1973 (Box 6)
    Volume #: 2, no.3 Issue #: 9
  - Bim Bam Boom, 1973 (Box 6)
    Volume #: 2, no.3 Issue #: 11
  - Bim Bam Boom, 1974 (Box 6)
    Volume #: 2, no.6 Issue #: 12
  - Soul, January 31, 1977 (Box 6)
    Volume #: 2 Issue #: 21
    Pam Grier and Richard Prior on cover
  - Dance Music Report, July 25, 1986 (Box 6)
    Volume #: 9 Issue #: 13
    Peter Gabriel on cover
  - Dance Music Report, August 5, 1988 (Box 6)
    Volume #: 11 Issue #: 13
    James Brown on cover
  - Dance Music Report, August 13-26, 1988 (Box 6)
    Volume #: 11 Issue #: 15
    Salt N Pepa on cover
  - Dance Music Report, October 8-21, 1988 (Box 6)
    Volume #: 11 Issue #: 19
    Karyn White on cover
  - Dance Music Report, December 26, 1988 - January 16, 1989 (Box 6)
    Volume #: 11 Issue #: 25
    Will to Power on cover
  - D.J. Direct, August - September (Box 6)
    Volume #: 1 Issue #: 1
    Jellybean Benitez on cover. Unknown year.
  - Where New Orleans, August 2001 (Box 6)
    Volume #: ? Issue #: ?
    Louis Armstrong on cover
  - Ego Trip, 1994 (Box 5)
    Nas on cover; premier issue
  - Ego Trip, 1994 (Box 5)
    Volume #: 1 Issue #: 2
    Method Man on cover
  - Ego Trip, 1995 (Box 5)
    Smif-N-Wessun on cover
  - Ego Trip, 1995 (Box 5)
    Volume #: 2 Issue #: 1
    Eazy-E on cover
  - Ego Trip, 1995 (Box 5)
    Volume #: 2 Issue #: 2
    Cypress Hill on cover
  - Ego Trip, 1995 (Box 5)
    Volume #: 2 Issue #: 3
    KRS-ONE on cover
  - Ego Trip, 1995 (Box 5)
    Volume #: 2 Issue #: 4
    Q-Tip/Pos/LargePro on cover
  - Ego Trip, 1996 (Box 5)
    Volume #: 2 Issue #: 5
    Ghostface Killer on cover
  - Ego Trip, 1996 (Box 5)
    Volume #: 2 Issue #: 6
    Redman on cover
  - Ego Trip, 1997 (Box 5)
    Volume #: 3 Issue #: 2
    Rakim on cover; 2 copies
  - Ego Trip, 1997 (Box 5)
    Volume #: 3 Issue #: 3
    Gangstarr on cover
  - Ego Trip, 1998 (Box 5)
    Volume #: 4 Issue #: 1
    Def Squad on cover
  - Life Sucks Die, 2001 (Box 5)
    Volume #: ? Issue #: 8
    illustrated cover
  - Tokion, 2002 (Box 5)
    Volume #: ? Issue #: 32
    Kool Herc and other various heads on cover